William A. O’Neill Papers VHP2005/12
CCSU Veterans History Project
William A. O'Neill Papers
Bulk, 1950-1954
1943, 1950-1954, 2005
VHP2005/12
CCSU Veterans History Project
39.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details William O’Neill’s military and combat experiences during his enlistment in the Korean War as well as the years following. the collection contains an oral history interview, personal and military documents, photographs and publications. The materials provide evidence of American troop training, combat activity, and enemy engagement. It highlights U.S. military moral and courage and offers insight into William O’Neill’s life prior to his tenure as Governor of Connecticut
O'Neill, William A., (William Atchinson), 1930-2007
Biographical/Historical note
With dreams of becoming a pilot William (Bill) Atchison O’Neill, a native of Hartford, Connecticut, and the 84th Governor of Connecticut enlisted in the United States Air Force in September of 1950. Bill performed his basic training at Lackland, Air Force Base in San Antonio, Texas and Sheppard Field in Wichita Falls, Texas. After basic training he attended gunnery training at Lowry Field in Denver, Colorado where he received instruction in firing 50 caliber M-2 machine guns. Bill went on to serve a year as gunner instructor and performed crew training at Randolph Field in San Antonio, Texas, before being assigned to Smoky Hill National Guard Range in Salinas, Kansas, and Stead Air Force Base in Reno, Nevada. His overseas assignments include Tokyo, Okinawa and North Korea.
While stationed at Kadena Air Force Base in Okinawa, Bill engaged in aerial bombing raids over much of North Korea. As the “Central Fire Control” or “Top Gunner” of a B-29 bomber Bill performed twelve night flights, each time engaging enemy aircraft while the pilots out maneuvered enemy flack.
Achieving the rank of Sergeant Airman First Class, Bill received the Air Medal, the Good Conduct Medal, the Korean Service Medal, the U.N. Service Medal and the National Service Medal. Returning to the United States he was assigned to Walker Air Force Base in Roswell, New Mexico and honorably discharged in 1953.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
Arrangement note
Series I: Presonal Papers
Series II: Publications
Series III: Multi-Media
United States. Air Force. Bomb Group, 19th.; United States. Air Force.; B-29 bomber; Interviews; Kadena Air Force Base (Okinawa-shi, Japan); Korea; Korean War, 1950-1953; Lowry Air Force Base (Colo.); Manuscript; Okinawa-shi (Japan); Photographs; Sheppard Field (Tex.); United States. Air Force -- Aerial gunners
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2005/12.I
  - Brien McMahon Correspondence – Letter, Sept. 14, 1950; VHP2005/12.I.1
  - Brien McMahon Correspondence – Telegram, circa 1950; VHP2005/12.I.2
  - Air Force Acceptance Letter, Sept. 26, 1950; VHP2005/12.I.3
  - U.S. Air Force Academy Reference, June 19, 1951; VHP2005/12.I.4
  - Medical flying Status, Sept. 13, 1951 - Nov. 14, 1953; VHP2005/12.I.5
  - Special Orders Number 215, Sept. 13, 1951; VHP2005/12.I.6
  - Individual Flight Record, Sept. 14 –Oct. 27, 1953; VHP2005/12.I.7
  - SAC Survival School Certificate, Feb. 19, 1953; VHP2005/12.I.8
  - Special Orders Number 111, April 21, 1953; VHP2005/12.I.9
  - Crew of the Month Commendation, Oct. 9, 1953; VHP2005/12.I.10
  - Discharge Certificate or DD256, Dec. 19, 1953; VHP2005/12.I.11
  - Discharge or DD214, 1953; VHP2005/12.I.12
  - Bill O’Neill’s Combat Mission, 1953; VHP2005/12.I.13
  - Medical authorization to report, Sept. 7, 1954; VHP2005/12.I.14
  - Synopsis of William O’Neill’s oral history interview, Aug, 18, 2005; VHP2005/12.I.15
  - Transcript of William O’Neill’s oral history interview, Aug, 18, 2005; VHP2005/12.I.16
- Series II: Publications, VHP2005/12.II
  - Ordnance Supply Catalog Addendum for M2 Browning machine gun, Dec. 30, 1943; VHP2005/12.II.1; 10.0 pages
  - 19th Bombardment Wing history pamphlet, Jun. 1, 1953; VHP2005/12.II.2; 13.0 pages
  - Superfort Gunner on Okinawa (Newspaper article), Circa 1950s; VHP2005/12.II.3
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2005/12.III
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2005/12.III
    - Bill loading twin 50 cals, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.1
    - Thomas Lane, Right Gunner, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.2
    - Clyde Robinson, Tail gunner, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.3
    - B-29 Radar Operator, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.4
    - B-29 Aircraft and 200 pound bombs, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.5
    - Crew lined up behind parachutes, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.6
    - Lieutenant Colonel Oholendt with crew, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.7
    - Crew laying out parachutes, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.8
    - Bill with crew wearing parachutes, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.9
    - Bill and crew with parachutes, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.10
    - Crew inspecting one another's parachutes, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.11
    - Top down view of B-29 bomber in flight, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.12
    - Side view of B-29 bomber in flight, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.13
    - Side view of B-29 bomber in flight with Okinawa islands below, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.14
    - B-29 bombers dropping bombs, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.15
    - Aerial view of Kadena Air Force Base, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.16
    - Aerial view of Kadena Air Force Base, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.17
    - Aerial view of Kadena Air Force Base, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.18
    - Aerial view of Okinawa coastline, 1953; VHP2005/12.III.19
    - William (Bill) A. O’Neill, 2005; VHP2005/12.III.20
  - Subseries A: Moving Images, VHP2005/12.IIIb
    - Oral History Interview, Aug. 18, 2005; VHP2005/12.IIIb.1; 1.0 dvd; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2005/12, Box VHP Interview #1)